Miami, FL 33155 MMWAHLER@GMAIL.COM 305.298.0377

www.linkedin.com/in/mmartinezwahler

STRATEGIC HUMAN RESOURCES LEADER

Accomplished, results-driven, passionate Human Resources professional with extensive experience managing full spectrum of human resources programs, services and functions. Broad knowledge of recruitment, employee relations, policy and procedure development, legal compliance and benefits design / administration. Strong communicator who uses relationship management and problem-solving skills to establish long-term partnerships at all levels of the organization. Fully bilingual English and Spanish.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

ALPHANET, INC - Coral Gables, FL

2010 - 2019

Human Resources Operations

- Facilitated management by providing human resources advice, counsel, and guidance for all decisions impacting staff; analyze information and trends to recommend best practices in employment and retention.
- Guided management and employee actions by researching, developing, writing, and updating policies, procedures, methods, and guidelines; communicate and reinforce organization culture and values.
- Oversaw compliance of federal, state and local legal requirements by studying existing and new legislation; anticipated legislation; enforced adherence to requirements; advised management on needed actions.
- Maintained work structure by creating job requirements and job descriptions for all positions.
- Trained managers to effectively coach, discipline, monitor and appraise employees; conducted orientation and training programs for new hires.
- Advised management on how best to resolve employee issues and concerns; counseled with employees and managers to resolve day to day issues.
- Planned and implementing talent acquisition strategies to recruit, source, test, interview and select best available talent.
- Trained and counseled managers on compliant candidate selection practices; conducted and analyzed exit interviews for possible changes.
- Implemented organizations compensation plan by conducting periodic compensation surveys; ensured annual reviews were scheduled and conducted, recommended, planned, and implemented compensation structure revisions.
- Executed employee benefit programs and informed employees of benefits by studying and assessing benefit needs and trends; recommended benefit programs to management, directed processing of benefit claims, obtained and evaluated benefit contract bids, awarded benefit contracts, designed and conducted educational programs on benefits awareness.
- Created management guidelines by preparing, updating, and recommending human resource policies and procedures.
- Audited the organizations HRIS and administer payroll function for several organization entities.

THE BLUE RESORT – Doral, FL

2008 - 2009

Human Resources Manager

- Executed all human resources policies, procedures for grand opening.
- Directed recruitment, orientation, training and development programs; resulted in lowering turnover.
- Provided leadership in employee relations, HR collaboration and recognition programs to enhance employee performance.

- Monitored performance evaluations and progressive discipline process.
- Committee member in development of 'luxury' criteria for recruitment and selection, performance evaluation, training and new hire integration.
- Attended and participated in professional group meetings; stayed informed of new trends and innovations in human resource management.
- Responded to, resolved sensitive inquires and complaints.

AMERICATEL CORPORATION - Miami, FL

2003 - 2008

Human Resources Generalist

- Assisted in execution of human resource management policies and procedures, company health and benefit plans.
- Prepared reviews, processed correspondence, reports, and forms and coordinated process of new hires.
- Facilitated recruitment including screening and interviewing.
- Data entry of employee time, maintained records, reports and statistical data in automated system.
- Processed payroll / benefit policies and processes.
- Provided day-to-day benefits administration.
- Assisted employees with any claim issues.
- Developed and scheduled benefits orientation and other benefit training, as well as 401(K) Compliance.
- Ensured implementation and compliance of affirmative action plan and EEO goals.
- Monitored organization's culture to support attainment of company's goals and promote employee satisfaction.

EDUCATION

Master of Science (M.S.), Human Resource Management Florida International University, Miami, FL

Bachelor's in Arts (B.A.), English / Communications, Spanish Language
Cabrini College, Philadelphia, PA

Member of National Society for Human Resources Management (SHRM)